<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Personal Blog</title>
<link>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A blog built with Quarto</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.24</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Day 5: ggplot2 and wrapup</title>
  <dc:creator>Emilia Morales</dc:creator>
  <link>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 5/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On the final day of the course, we had a session about the R package ggplot2, which is widely used for making graphs as there are a lot of options to personalize. After learning some theory behind it, the structure and some examples, we did some exercises ourselves by following a tutorial from NBIS. With this, we had a more basic exercise, and two more complex ones where we tried to recreate some public plots.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 5/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 5/chat.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Day 4: RNA-Seq data analysis with Nextflow and nf-core pipelines</title>
  <dc:creator>Emilia Morales</dc:creator>
  <link>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 4/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today we could run correctly the RNA-Seq pipeline with nextflow and nf-core. First, we tested the workflow manager nextflow by chaining the steps for qc and multiqc. Then we tested the ‘rnaseq’ pipeline by nf-core, which was built with nextflow. We used some of the RNA samples we had previously received, and ran the pipeline.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 4/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 4/chat.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Day 3: Nextflow, nf-core and AI in bioinformatics</title>
  <dc:creator>Emilia Morales</dc:creator>
  <link>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 3/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On the third day of the course, we worked with the workflow manager Netflow and nf-core pipelines, which are built around Nextflow. First, we copied the training material from the course. Then we run a script that did some basic commands, like breaking our input text into chunks of 6 characters, and capitalizing the letters or turning them backwards. For this, we learnt how the structure of a nextflow file should be and how to manipulate each part. Then we ran the script using pixi also. We learnt what each nextflow output file shows and why. Finally, we learnt how to clean up the working directory Nextflow generates when running our commands. Then, we tested an RNA sequencing analysis pipeline that is established in Nextflow. In the nextflow.config script we can set different parameters to be used in the further scripts, like for it to be executed with slurm, the default time limit for all processes and the project account. We then tried to run the first script that creates a transcriptome index file, using the tool salmon as a container. We couldn’t finish running this, as our cluster ran out of resources allocated for us. We learnt the theory behind nf-core, but couldn’t test it because of the resources.</p>
<p>Afterwards, we had a discussion about the use of AI in bioinformatics. It was interesting to learn that most Swedish universities allow the use of AI in official students’ works as long as it is disclosed.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 3/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 3/chat.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Day 2: Environments (Pixi), containers, slurm and QC exercises</title>
  <dc:creator>Emilia Morales</dc:creator>
  <link>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On the second day of the course, we performed quality control exercises in RNA sequencing samples with different methods. First, we worked with Pixi, an environment manager. We logged into the course server and created a Pixi environment, where we added conda-forge and bioconda also. Then, we added the dependencies we wanted, like quarto and fastqc. For this, we also practiced the use of screens. In my QC directory, I created sym links to the place where the actual sequencing fastq files were stored. In order to run the fastqc tool obtained with Pixi, we used SLURM, the job scheduling system. We can run simple commands like: run pixi srun -A hpc2n2025-203 -t 15:00 -n 1 fastqc –noextract -o fastqc data/sample_1.fastq.gz data/sample_2.fastq.gz Or we can write a script that runs it automatically (fastqc.sh) and then run it with sbatch. I can add run pixi within the script to obtain the tool. After running fastqc for all samples, we ran multiqc the same way, which summarises the output of the analysis of all the samples.</p>
<p>Then, we worked with containers, in this case Docker and Apptainer. For this, we have to download the image from their website (https://hub.docker.com/ or https://seqera.io/containers/) with apptainer pull XX. And we can execute the tool with apptainer exec or run interactively with apptainer shell XX. So we also ran the fastqc tool from apptainer with sbatch. Afterwards, we built our own container. For this we have to create a definition file (.def), build the container with apptainer build lolcow.sif lolcow.def and we can run it with apptainer run lolcow.sif. If we run apptainer exec XX, the arguments we give afterwards override the side the script.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 2/funny_cow.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="65" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Day 1: Data Management, Reproducible Research and How to make a Quarto blog</title>
  <dc:creator>Emilia Morales</dc:creator>
  <link>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 1/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="what-we-did-today" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-did-today">What we did today</h3>
<p>Today was the first day of the Applied Bioinformatics course. We learned in general about good practices in reproducible research, and we had an exercise with GitHub. We each created a branch with our name, and added our name to the README file. Then we merged this branch with someone else’s, resolving the emerging conflicts on. Then we merged this branch with someone else and so on, after multiple merges we created a student list with all of us in alphabetical order. It was challenging to go through with all the commands of pushing, pulling, committing, adding etc., but the more I practice, the easier it gets and the better it flows.</p>
<p>Then, we created a blog in VSCode which is published in Github pages with Quarto; this is where this entry is being written. This is a very useful tool, as it basically allows us to create a webpage in a simple way, which is backed up by Github. It’s again a good way to practice the commands related with version control in Github, and there’s a lot of applications to this. In this blog we will record and report everything we do throughout this course.</p>
<p>Today I’m testing different functionalities and things I can edit in the webpage when creating blog posts. The picture shows my dog, her name is Carmela and she’s very <strong>cute</strong></p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="information-to-remember" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="information-to-remember">Information to remember</h3>
<ul>
<li>We work with data, so it’s important to remember the FAIR principles about good data management practices:</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 1/images/fair.png" class="class img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<figcaption>FAIR principles</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li>Data management things to take into account:
<ul>
<li>The raw data should be in a folder alone where it won’t get altered, and separated from the code and results.</li>
<li>There should be information about what I did in every project folder, for me to remember later and also for others to understand if the code is to be passed on, preferably with a README file. It’s also advisable to write code in scripts combined with text for documentation and explanations (literate programming).</li>
<li>Name files properly without special characters and spaces.
<ul>
<li>I like to start with the date (YY.MM.DD_XX.X).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>Note:</strong> This material was taken from the course’s webpage.</p>
</blockquote>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>post</category>
  <guid>https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 1/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://emiliamoralest.github.io/blog/posts/Day 1/carmela.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
